A Guide to the Samuel M. Janney Papers, 1790-1922
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Papers, 1790-1922
Library of Virginia
24678
2 cubic feet
Samuel M. Janney
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased 7 October 1957.
Biographical Information
Samuel McPherson Janney was born 11 January 1801 in Loudoun County, Virginia, to Abijah Janney (1775-1842) and Jane McPherson Janney (1777-1813). After receiving some schooling, Janney was apprenticed at age fourteen to his uncle Phineas Janney (1775-1852) of Alexandria, Virginia, a commission merchant and iron importer. Janney later worked as a clerk and merchant. In 1828, he helped found a cotton factory at Occoquan, Prince William County, Virginia. However, it failed and Janney returned to Loudoun County and opened a girls' school called Springdale Boarding School in 1839. Janney retired about 1854 and devoted himself full time to the ministry, literature, and philanthropy. In 1869, President Ulysses S. Grant (1822-1885) appointed him Superintendent of Indian Affairs for the Northern Superintendency, a position which Janney held until 1871. Janney was a member of the Hicksite division of the Society of Friends, although he was on friendly terms with orthodox Quakers. Janney was an antislavery spokesman from the 1820s until the Civil War. He married Elizabeth Janney (1802-1893) 9 March 1826, and they had at least five children. Janney died in Loudoun County 30 April 1880.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1790-1922, of Samuel M. Janney (1801-1880) of Alexandria and Loudoun County, Virginia, consisting of: account books, accounts, agreements, brochures, clippings, commissions, correspondence, day books, deeds, eulogies, extracts, genealogies, grade cards, meeting minutes, memorials, memoirs, memorandum books, notebooks, notes, obituaries, poems, portraits, prayers, receipts, synopses, and travel journals. Collection is divided into four series. Series 1: Correspondence, 1815-1922. Series 2: Miscellaneous papers, 1790-1904. Series 3: Mercantile Accounts and Receipts of Phineas Janney, 1890-1891. Series 4: Account Books, Daybooks, Memorandum books, 1836-1870. The Friends Church Records, 1796-1799, 1815-1816, 1845-1850, three volumes of minutes of the Goose Creek Monthly Meetings in Loudoun County are filed in Church Records as accession 24678d.
Correspondence, 1815-1922, contains letters to and from Samuel M. Janney concerning the Society of Friends (Quakers), religion, slavery, education, business, Indian Affairs, publishing, and personal and family matters. Several letters deal with Quakers, both in Loudoun County, Virginia, and on a national level, and their religious beliefs. Also, letters deal with education, including correspondence about Janney's Springdale School for Girls in Loudoun County and exchange of ideas on education with William H. McGuffy (1800-1873) at the University of Virginia and with Horace Mann (1796-1859) of Massachusetts. Correspondence contains references to Janney's opposition to the institution of slavery. Also of interest is Janney's correspondence regarding his business interests, including his cotton factory in Occoquan, Prince William County, Virginia, and his store in Loudoun County. Collection also contains a commission as Superintendent of Indian Affairs for the Northern Superintendency from President Ulysses S. Grant (1822-1885) and Secretary of the Interior Jacob D. Cox (1828-1900), and correspondence addressed to him as superintendent. Letters between Janney and George P. Morris (1802-1864) and Samuel S. Randall (1809-1991) concern Janney's literary efforts. There are also several letters between Janney and his wife containing family and personal news. Also contains letters from Charles W. Kent (1860-1917) of the Library of Southern Literature to Cornelia Janney (1833-1922) concerning Samuel M. Janney, and letter to Congressman H. R. Snyder (1863-1937) of New York concerning the Bursum Indian Land Bill. Contains genealogical information on the Gray, Summerfield, and Tate families. Correspondents include Lyman C. Draper (1815-1891), John Jackson (1809-1855), Cornelia Janney, Elizabeth Janney (1802-1893), Charles W. Kent, Horace Mann, William H. McGuffy, GeorgeP. Morris, Dillwyn Parrish (1809-1886), Samuel S. Randall, and William Stabler (1795-1852).
Miscellaneous papers, 1790-1904, consists of accounts, agreements, brochures, clippings, deeds, eulogies, extracts, grade cards, memoirs, memorials, minutes, notebooks, notes, obituaries, poems, portraits, prayers, receipts, synopses, and travel journals. Of interest are an obituary, portrait, and synopsis of the funeral of Samuel M. Janney; manuscript chapter of Janney's memoirs; eulogies and memorials for Julia Rebecca Headley (1826-1842), John Janney (1827-1858), and Phineas Janney (1778-1852); extracts (abstracts) from the minutes of the yearly meeting of Quakers of Pennsylvania, New Jersey, Delaware, and the Eastern Parts of Maryland and Virginia, 1790, 1792; extracts from the minutes of the Yearly Meeting of Friends, 1864; letters to the Quarterly and Monthly Meeting of Friends in Great Britain, Ireland, and Elsewhere, 1792, 1801; manuscripts on various religious subjects; travel journals to the West Indies and to Canada and New England; notebook of John Janney; poems; accounts and receipts of Samuel M. Janney; miscellaneous papers including a deed from Israel Janney of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Phineas Janney of Alexandria, Virginia, selling Phineas all his rights to their father's estate, and an account of the last illness of Elizabeth Janney (d. 1809); and newspaper clippings.
Mercantile accounts and receipts, 1890-1891, of Phineas Janney (1842-1914) of Loudoun County, Virginia, consisting of routine bills for goods bought while a merchant in Loudoun County, Virginia. Some of the firms Janney did business with were Cushing and Company, John J. Thomson, and William T. Dixon of Baltimore, Maryland, and Joel J. Baily and Company of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
Account Books, Daybooks, Memorandum books, 1836-1870, consist of: daybook, 1836-1841, of S. M. Janney Cotton Factory; S. M. Janney executor's and trustee's accounts, 1841-1858; daybook, 1848-1854, for Phineas Janney's general store in Alexandria, Virginia; Farmers Bank of Virginia, Alexandria branch, in account with Phineas Janney's executors, 1852-1860; unidentified cash account book, 1850-1858; ledger, for John Janney's general store in Goose Creek, Loudoun County, 1854-1857, and S. M. Janney and Company general store in Goose Creek, 1859-1860; daybook, 1856-1861, for S. M. Janney and Company general store in Goose Creek; daybook, 1861-1869, for S. M. Janney and Company general store in Goose Creek; account book, 1840-1860, of William Tate; and memorandum book, 1840-1870, of William Tate.
Organization
Organized in three series. Series 1: Correspondence, 1815-1922. Series 2: Miscellaneous papers, 1790-1904. Series 3: Mercantile Accounts and Receipts of Phineas Janney, 1890-1891. Series 4: Account books, Daybooks, Memorandum books, 1836-1870.
Contents List
- Samuel M. Janney Correspondence, 1815-1922 (Folder 1-11)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Folder 1)
    - Letter, 25 October n.y., Elizabeth Janney, Lincoln [Loudoun County, Virginia], to daughter., a; 4 pages
    - Letter, 14 November n.y., from unknown correspondent, [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], to mother. Incomplete., b; 2 pages
    - Letter, n.d., T. M. Jewett, Ingledew, to sister., c; 4 pages
    - Letter, 12 March n.y., E[lizabeth] Janney to Samuel M. Janney, Baltimore, [Maryland]., d; 1 leaf
  - Correspondence, 1815 (Folder 2)
    - Letter, 28 July 1815, from Edward Stabler, New York, to John Janney, merchant, Alexandria, [Virginia]., a; 3 pages
  - Correspondence, 1820-1829 (Folder 3)
    - Letter, 6 June 1821, from Elizabeth Shreve, Trenton, [New Jersey], to Elizabeth Janney, Alexandria, [Virginia]., a; 3 pages
    - Letter, 3 October 1823, from Elizabeth Hopkins, South River, [Virginia?], to Elizabeth Janney, Alexandria., b; 2 pages
    - Letter, 25 September 1824, from George P. Morris, New York, [New York], to S[amuel] M. Janney, Alexandria., c; 2 pages
    - Letter, 6 June 1825, George P. Morris, New York, to Samuel M. Janney, Alexandria., d; 4 pages
    - Letter, 4 October 1825, Samuel M. Janney, New York, to Elizabeth Janney, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]., e; 4 pages
    - Letter, 10 October 1825, Elizabeth [Janney], Philadelphia, to Samuel M. Janney, Boston, [Massachusetts]., f; 4 pages
    - Letter, 5 November 1825, Elizabeth [Janney], Philadelphia, to Samuel M. Janney, Alexandria., g; 3 pages
    - Letter, 20 December 1825, George P. Morris, New York, to Samuel M. Janney, merchant, Alexandria., h; 4 pages
    - Letter, 18 April 1827, [Joseph Janney], Philadelphia, to Samuel M. Janney, Alexandria., i; 3 pages
    - Letter, 29 October 1827, [Samuel Janney], Baltimore, [Maryland], to [Elizabeth Janney], incomplete., j; 2 pages
    - Letter, 30 October 1827, Samuel M. Janney, Baltimore, to Elizabeth Janney, Alexandria., k; 3 pages
    - Letter, 19 March 1828, R. James Jenney [Janney], 39 Great James Street, Bedford Row, London [England], to P[hineas] Janney, Alexandria., l; 3 pages
  - Correspondence, 1830-1839 (Folder 4)
    - Letter, 29 May 1832, from S[amuel] M. Janney, Occoquan, [Virginia], to [Phineas Janney?], a; 4 pages
    - Letter, 8 February 1833, from Joseph Townsend and Nicholas Topplein, Baltimore, [Maryland], to Samuel M. Janney, Occoquan. Enclosure: testimony approved to disown Janney from the Ancient Society of Friends, dated 7 February 1833., b; 2 leaves
    - Letter, 16 November 1833, Samuel M. Janney, Winchester, [Virginia], to Elizabeth Janney, Occoquan, Prince William County., c; 4 pages
    - Letter, 28 February 1834, Rachel T. Tyson, Baltimore, to Elizabeth Janney, Occoquan, Prince William County., d; 4 pages
    - Letter, 27 October 1834, S[amuel] M. Janney, Occoquan and Baltimore, to Elizabeth Janney, Occoquan, Prince William County., e; 4 pages
    - Letter, 2 May 1836, Samuel M. Janney, New York, [New York], to Elizabeth Janney, Occoquan., f; 3 pages
    - Letter, 1 June 1838, Dillwyn Parrish, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to Samuel M. Janney, Occoquan., g; 3 pages
    - Letter, 8 October 1838, John Jackson, Darby, [Pennsylvania], to Samuel M. Janney, Occoquan., h; 3 pages
    - Letter, 1 January 1839, John Jackson, Darby, to Samuel M. Janney, Occoquan, Prince William County., i; 2 pages
    - Letter, 3 January 1839, Benjamin Hallowell, President of the Alexandria Lyceum, Alexandria, [Virginia], to [Samuel M. Janney]., j; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 30 May 1839, S[amuel] M. Janney, New York, to Elizabeth Janney, Occoquan, Prince William County., k; 2 pages
  - Letterbook, 1837-1839, 1841 (Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1840-1849 (Folder 6)
    - Letter, 11 July 1842, William Stabler, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Samuel M. Janney, Pursel's Store, Loudoun County, [Virginia]., a; 3 pages
    - Letter, 7 September 1842, William Stabler, Alexandria, to [Samuel M. Janney]., b; 4 pages
    - Letter, 17 September 1842, S[amuel] M. Janney, Springdale, [Loudoun County, Virginia], to Phineas Janney, Alexandria, D.C. [Virginia]., c; 4 pages
    - Letter, 14 May 1843, S[amuel] M. Janney, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to Elizabeth Janney, near Pursel's Store, Loudoun County., d; 3 pages
    - Letter, 6 June 1845, Elizabeth [Janney], Occoquan, [Virginia], to Samuel M. Janney, Springdale., e; 3 pages
    - Letter, 13 September 1845, [Samuel M. Janney], Springdale, to son [John Janney], [Philadelphia]., f; 4 pages
    - Letter, 7 November 1845, [Samuel M. Janney], Byberry, [Pennsylvania], to Elizabeth Janney, Pursell Store P.O., Loudoun County., g; 3 pages
    - Letter, 22 January 1846, Dillwyn Parrish, Philadelphia, to Samuel M. Janney, Pursell's Store, Loudoun County., h; 3 pages
    - Letter, 6 March 1846, John H. Janney, Alexandria, to sister., i; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 22 August 1846, Horace Mann, Boston, [Massachusetts], to S[amuel] M. Janney., j; 2 pages
    - Letter, 4 December 1846, Joseph Janney, Occoquan, to Elizabeth Janney, Purcell's Store, Loudoun County., k; 2 pages
    - Letter, 22 February 1847, William H. McGuffy, University of Virginia, [Charlottesville, Virginia], to Samuel M. Janney, Purcell's Store, Loudoun County., l; 3 pages
    - Letter, 11 May 1847, S[amuel] M. Janney, Philadelphia, to Elizabeth Janney, Springdale, Purcell's Store, Loudoun County, m; 2 pages
    - Letter, 1 January 1848, William H. McGuffy, University of Virginia, to Samuel M. Janney, Purcell's Store, Loudoun County., n; 3 pages
    - Letter, 2 May 1848, S[amuel] M. Janney, Wilmington, [Delaware], to Elizabeth Janney, Springdale, Purcell's Store, Loudoun County., o; 3 pages
    - Letter, 7 November 1848, S[amuel M. Janney], Little Britain, Lancaster County, [Pennsylvania], to Elizabeth Janney, Springdale, Purcell's Store, Loudoun County., p; 4 pages
  - Correspondence, 1850-1859 (Folder 7)
    - Letter, 30 August 1850, S[amuel] M. Janney, Unionville, Center County, Pennsylvania, to Elizabeth Janney, Springdale, Purcell's Store, Loudoun County, [Virginia]., a; 3 pages
    - Letter, 27 May 1851, Samuel S. Randall, Albany, [New York], to S[amuel] M. Janney, New York, New York., b; 2 pages
    - Letter, 21 July 1851, S[amuel] M. J[anney], Springdale, to S[amuel] S. Randall. Draft., c; 2 pages
    - Letter, 13 September 1851, [Samuel M. Janney], Springdale, to sister. Draft., d; 4 pages
    - Letter, 21 February 1852, S[amuel] M. Janney, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to E[lizabeth Janney]., e; 2 pages
    - Letter, 21 April 1852, sister, Springdale, to sister. Incomplete., f; 2 pages
    - Letter, 4 July 1852, unknown correspondent, West-Chester, [New York?], to brother. Incomplete., g; 4 pages
    - Memorandum, 4 March 1853, S[amuel] M. J[anney]'s testimony concerning W[illiam] Stabler., h; 2 pages
    - Letter, 18 March 1853, Samuel M. Janney, Alexandria, [Virginia], to Elizabeth Janney, Purcelville, Loudoun County., i; 3 pages
    - Letter, 18 May 1854, Lyman C. Draper, Corresponding Secretary, State Historical Society of Wisconsin, to Samuel M. Janney. Printed., j; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 20 February 1856, [Samuel M. Janney?] to Jane Johnson. Draft., k; 4 pages
    - Letter, 2 April 1857, S[amuel] M. Janney to Elizabeth Janney, Alexandria., l; 2 pages
    - Letter, 7 May 1857, S[amuel] M. Janney, Bucks County, Pennsylvania, to [Elizabeth Janney]., m; 4 pages
    - Letter, 18 September 1857, S[amuel] M. Janney, Mount Pleasant, Iowa, to Elizabeth Janney., n; 4 pages
    - Letter, 1 October 1857, S[amuel] M. Janney to [Elizabeth Janney]., o; 2 pages
    - Letter, 10 March 1858, S[amuel] M. Janney, near Purcelville, to T. M. Jewett. Draft., p; 3 pages
    - Letter, 11 April 1858, Dillwyn Parrish, Philadelphia, to [Samuel M. Janney]., q; 3 pages
  - Correspondence, 1860-1869 (Folder 8)
    - Letter, 13 March 1860, Townsend Warde, Librarian, Historical Society of Pennsylvania, to Samuel M. Janney, Purcellville, Virginia., a; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 4 May 1864, Elizabeth Janney, Meadow Lawn, [Loudoun County?, Virginia], to son., b; 4 pages
    - Letter, 30 March 1867, S[amuel M. Janney, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to Elizabeth Janney., c; 3 pages
    - Letter, 23 June 1867, S[amuel] M. Janney, Springdale, [Virginia], to William H. McGuffy. Draft., d; 3 pages
    - Letter, 28 August 1867, S[amuel] M. Janney, Newberry, [Pennsylvania?], to [Elizabeth Janney]., e; 4 pages
    - Commission, 28 April 1869, to Samuel M. Janney as the Superintendent of Indian Affairs for the Northern Superintendency durin ghte next term of four years. Signed by Jacob D. Cox, Secretary of the Interior and President Ulysses S. Grant., f; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 8 December 1869, Joseph Willetts, Presiding Officer, Brooklyn Social Union, to Samuel M. Janney, Superintendent, Dr. Edward Painter, and other agents of the Indians under the care of Friends in the Northern Superintendency, State of Nebraska., g; 2 pages
  - Correspondence, 1870-1879 (Folder 9)
    - Letter, 4 June 1870, S[amuel] M. Janney, Winnebajo Agency, Nebraska, to [Elizabeth Janney]., a; 2 pages
    - Letter, 21 July 1871, John Janney, Hull, Yorkshire, England, to Samuel M. Janney?], b; 3 pages
    - Letter, 9 February 1872, John Janney, Hull, Yorkshire, England, to Samuel M. Janney and S. H. Janney., c; 3 pages
    - Letter, 9 November 1875, S[amuel] M. Janney, Alexandria, [Virginia], to C[ornelia] Janney., d; 2 pages
    - Letter, 10 June 1877, Samuel M. Janney, Lincoln, Loudoun County, [Virginia], to Samuel S. Randall., e; 4 pages
    - Letter, 17 June 1877, S[amuel] S. Randall, Morrisania, New York City, [New York], to Samuel M. Janney., f; 4 pages
    - Letter, 27 August 1877, Samuel M. Janney, Occoquan, [Virginia], to C[ornelia] Janney, g; 2 pages
    - Letter, 3 March 1879, [Samuel M. Janney], Lincoln, Virginia, to Emmor K. Janney. Draft., h; 2 pages
  - Correspondence, 1885 (Folder 10)
    - Letter, 2 February 1885, Elizabeth Janney, Lincoln, [Virginia], to daughter [Cornelia Janney]., a; 4 pages
    - Letter, 20 October 1885, T. M. Jewett, Ingledew, to sister., b; 3 pages
  - Correspondence, 1893-1922 (Folder 11)
    - Letter, 30 December 1893, Robert M. Janney, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to cousin Cornelia Janney, Lincoln, Loudoun County, [Virginia]., a; 3 pages
    - Letter, 4 February 1904, E. T. Gray, Newark, New Jersey, to cousin William. Enclosure: copies of the the Tate and Gray family genealogies., b; 2 pages and 6 leaves
    - Letter, 7 November 1907, Charles W. Kent, Literary Editor, Library of Southern Literature, University of Virginia, [Charlottesville, Virginia], to Cornelia Janney, Lincoln, Loudoun County., c; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 15 November 1907, Charles W. Kent, Literary Editor, Library of Southern Literature, University of Virginia, to Cornelia Janney, Lincoln, Loudoun County., d; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 2 February 1916, W. S. Greenway, General Auctioneer, Roanoke, Virginia, to William T. Shoemaker, Lincoln, Virginia., e; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 8 October 1920, George A. Walton, Principal, George School, Pennsylvania. Form letter concerning raise in tuition., f; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 17 December 1922, to H. R. Snyder, House of Representatives, Washington D.C. Form letter concerning the Bursum Indian Land Bill. Two copies., g; 2 leaves
- Samuel M. Janney Miscellaneous Papers, 1790-1904 (Folder 12-28)
  - Papers relating to death of Samuel M. Janney, 1880 (Folder 12)
    - A Short Synopsis of the Principle Points, in Remarks Made at the Funeral of Our Beloved Father Samuel M. Janney, 1880., a; 4 leaves
    - Envelope, n.d., Elizabeth Janney from S. T. Nichols, by request of Clara C. Janney., b; 1 item
    - Obituary, 1880, of Samuel M. Janney., c; 1 leaf
    - Portrait, n.d., of Samuel M. Janney, d; 1 item
  - Chapter 25 [manuscript] of Samuel M. Janney's Memoirs, 1880 (Folder 13)
  - Eulogy for Julia Rebecca Headley, 1842 (Folder 14)
  - Memorial for John Janney, 1858 (Folder 15)
  - Memoirs of Phineas Janney, 1852 (Folder 16)
  - Extracts, Minutes of the Yearly Meeting of Quakers of Pennsylvania, New Jersey, Delaware, and the Eastern Parts of Maryland and Virginia, 1790, 1792 (Folder 17)
    - Extracts, 1790, Minutes of the Yearly Meeting of Quakers of Pennsylvania, New Jersey, Delaware, and the Eastern Parts of Maryland and Virginia., a; 3 pages
    - Extracts, 1792, Minutes of the Yearly Meeting of Quakers of Pennsylvania, New Jersey, Delaware, and the Eastern Parts of Maryland and Virginia., b; 8 pages
  - Letters to the Quarterly and Monthly Meeting of Friends in Great Britain, Ireland, and America and Elsewhere, 1792, 1801 (Folder 18)
    - Letter, 12 June 1792, From a Meeting for Sufferings in New York to the Quarterly and Monthly Meetings of Friends in Great-Britain, Ireland, and America., a; 3 pages
    - Epistle, 20 May-2 June 1801, From the Yearly Meeting, Held in London, to the Quarterly and Monthly Meetings of Friends in Great Britain, Ireland, and Elsewhere., b; 3 pages
  - Extracts from the Minutes of the Yearly Meeting of Friends, 1864 (Folder 19)
  - Manuscripts on Various Religious Subjects (Folder 20)
  - Journal of Voyage to the West Indies, 22 March-21 May 1823 (Folder 21)
  - Journal of Voyage to New England and Canada, 30 May-26 July 1826 (Folder 22)
  - Student Notebook (Folder 23)
  - Manuscript Volume of Poetry (Folder 24)
  - Poems and Brochures, 1822, 1914 (Folder 25)
    - Poem, 15 February 1822, On Memory., a; 3 pages
    - Poems, 1914, The Wedding, February 23, 1864 and The Golden Wedding, February 23, 1914., b; 3 leaves
    - Poem, n.d., A Night Scene: Among the Mountains of Virginia., c; 3 pages
    - Poem, n.d., untitled., d; 2 leaves
    - Brochure, n.d., for the Library of Southern Literature., e; 6 pages
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1839-1904 (Folder 26)
    - Account, 31 January 1839, for sales of one hundred and fifty barrels white wheat flour received per brig Mary Helen and sold on account of Messrs. William Fowle[?] and Son., a; 3 pages
    - Receipt, 5 July 1852, for rent., b; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 10 June 1881, to William T. Shoemaker from T. Scott and Son of Baltimore, Maryland., c; 1 leaf
    - Letterhead, 11 February 1904, for Horlick's Food Company, Racine, Wisconsin., d; 1 leaf
    - letter, n.d., from an unknown correspondent to an unknown recipient regarding failure to receive a check in payment of money owed., e; 2 pages
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1809-1884 (Folder 27)
    - Account, 1809, of Elizabeth Janney's last illness., a; 5 pages
    - fragment, 1827, of minutes from a Friends meeting., b; 1 leaf
    - Agreement, 13 October[?] 1838, between Samuel M. Janney and S. Tansill., c; 1 leaf
    - Deed, 10 August 1840, between Israel Janney of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and Phineas Janney of Alexandria, Virginia, by which Israel Janney signs over all interest in their father's estate., e; 3 pages
    - fragment, 13 September 1851, of religious essay by Samuel W. Janney., f; 1 leaf
    - Account, 1852, of the death of Phineas Janney., g; 1 leaf
    - Report card, 4 January 1884, for Sadie Shoemaker attending Sub-District School No. 5, Mt. Gilead Township, Loudoun County, Virginia., h; 1 leaf
    - fragment, n.d., containing comment on private devotion., i; 2 pages
    - fragment, n.d., containing comment on peace and war., j; 1 leaf
    - Analysis, n.d., of the Twenty-third Psalm., k; 1 leaf
    - note, n.d., on Samuel Janney's meeting with the Omaha Indians., l; 1 leaf
    - Incomplete essay, n.d., on Society of Friends and Methodists., m; 4 pages
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1846-1880 (Folder 28)
    - Clipping, 1840, from the Philadelphia Age, meeting at the Historical Society and formal presentation of the William Penn papers., a; 6 leaves, photocopies
    - Clipping, 29 May 1846, from the Winchester Republican., b; 4 pages, photocopies
    - Clipping, 25 March 1852, from the Baltimore American containing a review of Samuel M. Janney's The Life of William Penn., c; 1 leaf, photocopy
    - Clipping, [1880], from an unknown newspaper being an obituary of Samuel M. Janney., d; 1 leaf, photocopy
    - Clipping, n.d., from an unknown newspaper about a solar eclipse in New England 19 May 1780., e; 2 leaves, photocopies
- Phineas Janney Mercantile Accounts, 18901-1891 (Folder 29)
  - Accounts, 1890-1891 (Folder 29)
    - Account, 29 April 1890, with John J. Thomsen of Baltimore, Maryland., a; 2 leaves
    - Account, 1 May 1890, with Cushing and Company of Baltimore, Maryland., b; 2 leaves
    - Account, 5 May 1890, with George Blome and Son of Baltimore, Maryland., c; 1 leaf
    - Account, 8 May 1890, with William T. Dixon and Brother of Baltimore, Maryland., d; 1 leaf
    - Account, 23 May 1890, with Strawbridge and Clothier of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania., e; 1 leaf